<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Edinburgh, at the Parliament-House, February 13. 1661.</title>
            <author>Argyll, Archibald Campbell, Earl of, 1629-1685</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3653A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R172501</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53298940</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53298940</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179730</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01426)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179730)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2798:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Edinburgh, at the Parliament-House, February 13. 1661.</title>
                  <author>Argyll, Archibald Campbell, Earl of, 1629-1685</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Argyll, Archibald Campbell, --  Earl of, 1629-1685 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Trials (Treason) --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proceedings">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179730:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> At the Parliament-Houſe, <hi>February</hi> 13. 1661.</head>
            <p>THe, Marqueſs of <hi>Argyle</hi> (being accuſed of High Treaſon, at the inſtance of Sir <hi>John Fletcher,</hi> his Majeſties Advocat for his Intereſt) was brought to the Bar: His Lordſhip humbly deſired but to ſpeak a few words before read-the Indictment; aſſuring to ſpeak nothing in the Cauſe it ſelf. Whereupon he was removed a little, and after ſome Debate, the Houſe reſolved that the ſaid Indictment ſhould be firſt read. Then his Lordſhip deſired that a Bill which he had cauſed his Advocats give in to the Lords of the Articles, (deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a precognition, with many reaſons urging the neceſſity of it) to which he had received no anſwer, might be read before the ſaid Indictment; which being likewiſe refuſed, the ſaid Indictment was firſt read; and after the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, the Marqueſs (being put off his firſt thoughts) was compelled to this extemporary Diſcourſe following, as it was faithfully collected from ſeveral Hands, who writ when his Lordſhip ſpoke.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY Lord Chancellor, Before <hi>I</hi> ſpeak any thing, I ſhall humbly proteſt my words may not be wreſted, but that <hi>I</hi> may have Charity to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved; and <hi>I</hi> ſhall with God's aſſiſtance, <hi>ſpeak truth</hi> from my heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſhall, my Lord, reſume <hi>Mephiboſheths</hi> anſwer to <hi>David,</hi> (after a great Rebellion, and himſelf evil reported of) ſaith he, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.30. <hi>Yea, let him take all, for as much as my Lord the King is come home again in peace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his own houſe;</hi> So ſay I, ſince it has pleaſed God Almighty graciouſly to return his Sacred Majeſty to the Royal Exerciſe of his Government over theſe Nations, to which he has undoubted Right, and was moſt unjuſtly and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently thruſt therefrom by the late tyrannizing Uſurpers.</p>
                  <p>It is, my Lord, exceeding matter of joy to us all, that that Iron-yoke of Uſurpation (under which we have theſe many years ſadly groaned) is now broke, and with much freedom this High and Honourable Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are meeting together, under the refreſhing warm Beams of his Majeſties Royal Government, (ſo much <hi>longed for by our almost ſtarved expectations;</hi>) and <hi>I</hi> do earneſtly wiſh his Royal Preſence upon his Royal Throne amongſt us; but ſince at this time that great happineſs cannot probably be expected, <hi>I</hi> am glad that <hi>his Majeſties Prudence has ſingled out</hi> ſuch a qualified and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy perſon as my Lord Commiſſioner his Grace to repreſent himſelf, whoſe unſpotted Loyalty to his Majeſty we can all witneſs.</p>
                  <p>I cannot, my Lord, but acknowledge, that theſe two <hi>grand Mercies,</hi> which comfortably attends my preſent condition; one is, The high thoughts I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly entertain of that tranſcendent and Princely clemency wherewith his Sacred Majeſty is ſo admirably delighted, abundantly evidenced by many
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179730:2"/>noted and <hi>ſignal teſtimonies</hi> in all the ſteps of his Majeſties carriage; as thoſe moſt gracious Letters, Declarations, and that free and moſt ample Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity, granted to all his Majeſties Subjects, (excepting ſome of the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat Murderers of his Royal Father) to eradicate any timorous Jealouſies of his Majeſties gracious Pardon (which might haply ariſe by ſerious reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) convincing them forceably of their own miſcarriages in theſe unhappy times of diſtraction: The effects, my Lord, of which Princely deportment, <hi>I</hi> am confidently hopeful, his Majeſty has experimentally, and ſhall find, prove one effectual Cement to concilliate the moſt antimonarchick and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected perſons [excepting ſome of thoſe barbarous Phanaticks] in <hi>all his Majeſties Dominions,</hi> moſt willingly to the ſubjection of his Majeſties Royal Scepter; and with a perfect hatred abominate all diſloyal Practices in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or others, in all time coming.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, my Lord, When <hi>I</hi> conſider that my Judges are not ſuch as we had of late, [Strangers,] but my own Countrymen; both which jointly [together with the real ſenſe and ſolid convictions <hi>I</hi> have of my innocency of theſe calumnies moſt unjuſtly charged upon me] encourages my hopes the rather, to expect ſuch dealing, as will moſt ſympathize with that clement hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour [to which his Sacred Majeſty hath ſuch a natural propenſity] and ſuch equal adminiſtration of Juſtice [void of all byaſſing prejudices] as will be moſt ſuitable to ſuch a high and honourable Meeting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſhall therefore, my Lord, deſire to uſe <hi>Paul</hi>'s anſwer for himſelf, being accuſed of his Countrymen, may not be miſtaken, he having a learned Orator <hi>Tertullus</hi> accuſing him, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.14, 15, 16. as <hi>I</hi> have my Lord Advocat; <hi>Paul</hi>'s was Hereſie, mine of another nature; but <hi>I</hi> muſt ſay with him, That the things they alledge againſt me cannot be proved; but this <hi>I</hi> confeſs, in the way allowed by ſolemn Oaths and Covenants, <hi>I</hi> have ſerved God, my King, and Country [as he ſaid] which they themſelves alſo allow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſhall, my Lord, remember [not with repining, but for information] my hard uſage, never having had my Hearing, nor allowance of Pen, Ink, nor Paper, nor the comfort of ſeeing my Friends freely, until <hi>I</hi> received this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which was in effect a Load above a Burden; Enemies, both <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> out of Malice calumniating me for all the ſame things, excepting what relates to his Majeſties moſt Royal Father of ever glorious memory.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, my Lord, <hi>I</hi> beg charity and patient hearing, not doubting but the wiſdom and goodneſs of the Parliament will be ſo favourable, and not as the inconſiderate multitude [as a learned and able man<note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Walter Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leighs</hi> Preface to to the Hiſtory of the World.</note> writes, ſays he,] As we ſee in experience, That Dogs they always bark at them they know not; and that it is their nature, to accompany one another in thoſe clamours; ſo it is with the inconſiderate multitude, who wanting that vertue which we call honeſty in all men; and that ſpecial gift of God [which we call charity in Chriſtian men] condemn with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hearing, and wound without offence given, led thereunto by uncertain report only; which his Majeſty King <hi>James</hi> only acknowledges to be the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Lies: I ſhall not deſire to be in the leaſt miſtaken by any that hear me: But ſure I am, it is pertinently applicable to my caſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179730:2"/>
                     <hi>I</hi> intreat your Lordſhip likewiſe to conſider the words of another notable man,<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Speed</hi> in his Hiſtory.</note> who ſays, As the tongues of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites are ill Ballances to weigh the Vertues of Princes and great Men, ſo neither ſhould theirs, nor other mens ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes be looked upon as they are drawn with the deformed Pencil of Envy or Rancour; which do always attend Eminency, whether in place or vertue. <hi>I</hi> ſhall not, my Lord, be ſo preſumptuous as to arrogate any thing to my ſelf in this, only <hi>I</hi> want not the two Companions; for I am but a weak man, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to many failings and infirmities, [whereof I do not purge my ſelf] for as we muſt confeſs to God Almighty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.3. if he ſhould mark iniquity, who can ſtand? Neither ſhall I ſay, That there cannot a Hole be diſcovered [as the Proverb is] in my Coat; and it cannot but be ſo with any, ſpecially ſuch as have labour'd in ſuch times buſineſs; but I bleſs the Lord, that in theſe things which have been, and are here caſt upon me, I am able to make the falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and miſconſtruction of them palpably appear.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, before I mention any thing in particular, I muſt ſhew this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Meeting of Parliament, and all that hear me, [who doublteſs have vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous apprehenſions of my being preſent in this condition,] that I am here ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as my misfortune, nor my injury; wherein I deſire to explain the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Aristotle</hi> does very well; calling injuries ſuch things as are done purpoſely with a wicked mind; and misfortunes, ſuch things as are done with a good mind, though the events prove bad, yet we could not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee them.</p>
                  <p>So, My Lord, I ſhall take God to record (who muſt judge me one day) upon my Conſcience, That what I did, flowed not from any injurious principle to any, though <hi>I</hi> acknowledge the events were not ſtill ſo ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (which was my misfortune) indeed; but it has been my Lot often in theſe times, wherein <hi>I</hi> and many others have been inevitably involved, to be by the malicious tongues of my calumniating enemies, miſconſtructed for the worſt; yea, even in many things that the Lord was pleaſed to make ſuccesfull: for the truth of this, <hi>I</hi> may, I hope, ſafely appeal to many in this Honourable Houſe, who can abundantly witneſs my faithfull and Loyal En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours for both my King and Native Country: whereof <hi>I</hi> ſhould be very ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be an Herauld my ſelf, were not the contrary ſo impudently affirmed. There are five main calumnies that <hi>I</hi> deſire, my Lord, to ſatisfie all that hear me a little in; to the end that the reſt of leſs moment may be likewiſe in its own due time heard afterward abſtract more from perſonal prejudice.</p>
                  <p>The firſt Calumny is, my Lord, concerning that horrid and unparrallel'd Murder of his late Royal Majeſty of eternally bleſſed Memory; <hi>I</hi> do here publickly declare, that <hi>I</hi> neither deſire, nor deſerve the leaſt countenance or favour, if <hi>I</hi> was either acceſſory to it, or on the counſel or knowledge of it; which to make clearly appear, is under Oath of the Parliament Books 1649, whereof <hi>I</hi> was the firſt ſtarter my ſelf, to the intent we might both vindicate ourſelves, and endeavour a diſcovery, if any amongſt us had any acceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that horrid and Villanous Crime; as alſo in my latter Will which <hi>I</hi> made going to <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1655 or 1656, fearing what poſſibly might hereafter be obtruded by any upon me or my Family upon that account, <hi>I</hi> ſet it down to clear my poſterity, That <hi>I</hi> was altogether free of that deteſtable and execrable Crime, or of any prejudice to his Majeſty, in either perſon or Government: <hi>I</hi> left this with a very worthy Gentleman, <hi>I</hi> believe well known
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179730:3"/>to your Lordſhip, and never ſaw it ſince, ſo your Lordſhip may be pleaſed if you will to call for it and try the truth; whatſoever other thing may be in it, I hope, my Lord, this opportunity is a mercy to me, to have that vile ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny amongſt many others againſt me to be cleared.</p>
                  <p>And, my Lord, to make this particular yet more evident, <hi>I</hi> did ſtill, and do poſitively aſſert, that I never ſaw that monſtruous Uſurper, <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> in the face, nor ever had the leaſt correſpondence with him, or any of that Sectarian Army, untill the Commands of the Committee of Eſtates ſent me, with ſome other Noblemen and Gentlemen to the Border, in <hi>anno</hi> 1648, to ſtop his march into <hi>Scotland</hi> after thoſe who retired from <hi>Preſton</hi> fight; neither after he left the Border in the year 1648, did I ever correſpond with him, or any of that Sectarian Army, ſo unſatisfied was I with their way, after the wicked and ſiniſtrous courſes he and they were upon afforded evident preſumptions for us to apprehend, that he and they intended prejudice to his Royal Majeſty; only one letter I received from Sir <hi>Atrhur Heſilrig,</hi> to which I returned anſwer, That he might ſpare his pains in writing to me, for I bleſſed the Lord who taught me by his Word, <hi>To fear God and honour the King, and not to meddle with them that were given to change;</hi> though Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> be now dead, yet he acknowledged to ſeveral in the Tower, that he ſtill had my Letter: and when I was there, I often deſired he might be poſed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined about it; which I can preſently inſtruct. And during, my Lord, my being in <hi>England</hi> neither in <hi>London</hi> nor <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1647. There was not any thing ſo much as mentioned concerning his late Majeſties perſon; all that ever I heard of, was in publick Parliament 1647. The Commiſſioners papers at <hi>London,</hi> and the Committee Books at <hi>Newcastle</hi> will clear this fully.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond calumny is anent the inhumane Murder of Duke <hi>James Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton:</hi> My Lord, it's well known my great reſpect to that truly Noble and Worthy perſon, whereof (upon all occaſions) I gave ample teſtimonies, and can yet convince any of his friends with the reality of it; and evidenced my true ſorrow for the wicked cruelty committed upon him; But indeed I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny I refuſed to complement <hi>Cromwell</hi> on his behalf, he having, my Lord, been immediatly preceeding, ſo inſtrumental, and ſo very active in that moſt horrid and lamentable Murder of his late Sacred Majeſty, and if I had done otherwiſe, undoubtedly it had been a more black Article in that Lybel now read, than any that is in it.</p>
                  <p>The third Calumny is, That which breeds a great part of theſe groundleſs Clamours (tho it be not in the Indictment) is my Lord Marquis of <hi>Huntly's</hi> death; wherein <hi>I</hi> may truly ſay, I was as earneſt to preſerve him, as poſſibly I could, (which is very well known to many in this Honourable Houſe) and my not prevailing, may ſufficiently evidence I had not ſo great a ſtroke nor power in the Parliament as is lybelled; And, my Lord, for his Eſtate, I had nothing in that, but for my own abſolutely neceſſary relief, and was ever moſt willing to part with any intereſt I had therein, getting his Friends (who profeſſed much Zeal for the ſtanding of the Family] engaged for warrandiſe to me, of any portion that ſhould happen to fall my ſatisfaction; and to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that I was no means to harm the Family, <hi>I</hi> ſtood with my Right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt all Fines and Forefeitures of Bonds, and accompted for anything I could receive; and to manifeſt yet furder, that the burden of that Family was not from any extrinſick cauſe to themſelves, I have under the old Marquis his own hand, and his Sons, <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Gordon,</hi> who was a very worthy young
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179730:3"/>Nobleman, the juſt Inventory of their Debts, amounting to about one mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of Merks, in <hi>anno</hi> 1640. It would I fear, my Lord, conſume too much of the Parliaments precious time, to hear many other circumſtances to make this particular more clear, which I ſhall at this time forbear.</p>
                  <p>The fourth Calumny is, the death of the Marquis of <hi>Montroſe;</hi> There are many in this Houſe, my Lord, who know very well <hi>I</hi> refuſed to meddle either in the matter or manner of it; and ſofar were we from having any particular Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels at one another, that in <hi>anno</hi> 1645, he and I were fully agreed upon Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and Conditions contained in a Treaty paſt betwixt us; the Gentleman is yet alive who carried the meſſages both by Word and Writing betwixt us; and it was neither his fault nor mine that the buſineſs did not end at that time, which is know to all, proved very obnoxious to the Kingdom thereafter.</p>
                  <p>The fifth Calumny is concerning my dealing with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> after <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſight; It is well known, my Lord, to many, that my ſelf, and the Gentlemen of <hi>Argyleshire,</hi> my Kinſmen, Vaſſals and Tennents, endeavoured cordially to engage all their Neighbours about them on all hands, againſt the <hi>English,</hi> which they did not prevail in, but was moſt unhappily made known to the <hi>English</hi> Commanders for the time; which they cauſed immediatly publiſh, as a very notable Diſcovery, in their news Books; which occaſioned two ſad diſad van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to us: for they not only cruſhed our Attempts in the infancy, but alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined the ſeverer Reſolutions againſt us; whereby two ſtrong Regiments of Foot, <hi>Overtouns</hi> and <hi>Reads,</hi> and very near the number of one of Horſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of one <hi>Blackamour,</hi> were ſent to <hi>Argyle,</hi> and when <hi>Dean</hi> came there, it pleaſed God to viſit me with a great diſtemper of ſicknes, as Doctor <hi>Cunninghame,</hi> and many others who were with me, can witneſs, what my Lord, I was preſt to when <hi>I</hi> was violently in their hands, may be inſtructed by the paper it ſelf, written by <hi>Deans</hi> mans own hand yet extant to ſhew, which <hi>I</hi> did abolutely refuſe upon all the hazard of the uttermoſt of their malice; as alſo what <hi>I</hi> was neceſſitate to do, is likewiſe ready to be ſhown, whereby I was ſtill continued their Priſoner upon demand.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall, my Lord, add one Reaſon more to clear this (beſides many other weighty publick Reaſons and Conſiderations, which I ſhall forbear to mention at this time, it being more natural to bring them in by way of Defences af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward) my own Intereſt, and of all Noblemen and Superiors in <hi>Scotland.</hi> It may be rationally preſumed, that I had been a very ſenſeleſs fool, if ever I had been for promoting ſuch an Authority or intereſt over me, as levelled all, and was ſo totally deſtructive to all that differenced my ſelf and other No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen, from their own Vaſſals, (which many ſays I was too earneſt in) Yea, it being abſurdly derogative to all true Nobility; and my Anceſtors and I (as is ſaid in that Libel having had ſo many Titles of Honour, Dignity, and eminent places of Truſt conferred upon us by his Majeſties Royal Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors and himſelf, (all for our conſtant Loyalty and adherence to the Crown at all occaſions (as the Records and Hiſtories of this antient Kingdom holds forth, beſides the Narratives of all our Grants) and aſſerting the juſt privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thereof againſt all oppoſers) <hi>I</hi> did, my Lord, ever (even when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were at the intollerable height of Uſurpation) declare my true abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to a Common-wealth Government, which was well known to them all. <hi>I</hi> was not indeed, my Lord, very diſſatisfied when there was Rumours ſpread abroad of <hi>Cromwels</hi> being made a King, as ſome here preſent can witneſs: For <hi>I</hi> told them it was a moſt probable way for his Majeſty; and the more it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179730:4"/>were incouraged, would tend the more to <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and their deformed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealths Governments Ruine, and promote his Majeſties juſt intereſt the more. My Lord, <hi>I</hi> ſhall not much blame my Lord Advocat for doing his endeavour [it being an eſſential part of his Function to accuſe] but <hi>I</hi> muſt ſay, That it is very hard meaſure, that ſo able a man has taken near as many Months, in taking pains to prompt as many Enemies as his perſwaſions could poſſibly invite, to vent out the higheſt notes of their malice, and laying out ſearch by them for, and collecting all the bad Reports, or rather, to give them their genuine term, <hi>I</hi> may call them a confuſed Maſs of the common Claſhes of the Country, thereby to deviſe miſconſtructions of all the publick actings, of both Parliaments and Comittees, during the late troubles, and with ſtrange and remote inferences to adduce all thoſe to the channel of my particular actings; he has taken, <hi>I</hi> ſay, my Lord, as many Months, as <hi>I</hi> have had days, to anſwer them, being an exceeding diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. But my Lord, that's not all, <hi>I</hi> am like wiſe extreamly troubled, that he labours in that Libel all along to draw an obſcure vail of perpetual oblivion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all my good ſervices; and ſpecially my faithful and loyal endeavours in reſtoring of his Sacred Majeſty to the Crown of this his moſt Antient Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the exerciſe of his Majeſties Royal Authority therein, with my cordial endeavours for his Majeſties Reſtitution to the reſt of his Dominions alſo, which his Majeſty both knows, and has been pleaſed often to acknowledge it to have been good ſervice; yea, and many preſent in this Honourable Houſe knows, that <hi>I</hi> extended both my Zeal and Affection to the utmoſt of my Power for his Majeſties Service in that particular, which <hi>I</hi> willingly acknowledge nothing, my Lord, but my duty, whereunto <hi>I</hi> was tyed both by natural civil, and Chriſtian Bands to my Sovereign, and ſpecially ſuch a King of whom <hi>I</hi> may ſay well [as <hi>I</hi> have often affirmed] That he is a King in whom the Lord has been pleaſed to take ſuch pleaſure, as to poſſeſs his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty with ſo many ſuperlative degrees of Excellency, that will certainly exalt his Majeſties Fame both in our Age, and to ſubſequent Poſterity, above all the Monarchs in the World; ſo, that my Lord, we may conſequently diſcover a high Demonſtration of the Lords ſingular Kindneſs, and ſpecial providenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al care for us his Majeſties Subjects, in preſerving ſuch a rich Bleſſing as his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty (in whom the Happineſs of theſe Nations is wrapt up) under the ſafe Wings of his Divine Protection, <hi>I</hi> may ſay,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal:</hi> 56.2.</note> even when the extravagant malice of men would have ſwallowed him up.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After my Lord had ended this diſcourſe (being heard by all very atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, without any Interruptions) Thus the Lord Advocate ſpoke to my Lord Chancellor. My Lord, what can the Marquiſs of <hi>Argyle</hi> ſay to the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Stirling, in anno</hi> 1648. The Marquiſs replyed, That he found my Lord Advocat endeavoured to bring him to debate the particulars [which he hoped ſhould be cleared at another more convenient time) and waved anſwering the thing it ſelf, but inſiſted thus: My Lord Chancellor, <hi>I</hi> have [informative only] hinted a little at the main things which I am often charged with, my Memory cannot fully reach all, neither will time permit to circumſtantiat theſe particulars, which <hi>I</hi> have only touched in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; nor is it my purpoſe at preſent to fall on the debate of any of that Libel [not having yet conſulted the Proceſs] by reaſon theſe Advocats your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179730:4"/>was pleaſed to allow me, have not yet all embraced, and the excuſes of my ordinary Advocats [in whom <hi>I</hi> had confidence] being admitted as relevant. And thir Gentlemen, that has been pleaſed [in obedience to your Lordſhips Command] to come here with me, not being much acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with matters of this weight, and not having imbraced till within theſe two or three days: So that they are ſtrangers altogether to my caſe] <hi>I</hi> ſhall therefore my Lord, humbly deſire, that a competent time may be allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed me, that <hi>I</hi> may prepare my Defences, and <hi>I</hi> ſhall [God willing] abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly clear every particular in that Libel. And alſo my Lord, I humbly deſire, that theſe other Advocats, who were ordained by your Lordſhips to aſſiſt me [and after the Honourable Lords of Articles had heard them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected their excuſes] may be now reordained to conſult and appear for me.</p>
            <p>The Marquiſs his Advocates entered a Proteſtation, that what ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to eſcape them in pleading [either by word or Writ, for the Life, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Eſtate of the ſaid Noble Marquiſs, their Client might not thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be obtruded to them as Treaſonable, whereupon they took inſtruments.</p>
            <p>The Marquiſs aſſured my Lord Chancellor, That he knew not of any ſuch Proteſtation to be preſented, and that it flowed ſimply of themſelves; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon my Lord Chancellor deſired the Marquiſs and his Advocats to remove, till the Houſe ſhould conſider both of my Lords deſire, and the Advocats Proteſtation.</p>
            <p>The Marquiſs and his Advocats being removed. The Houſe [after ſome ſmall debate] reſolved, as to my Lord Marquiſs deſires, his Lordſhip ſhould have till the 26 of <hi>February</hi> to give in his Defences in Writ, and ordained Mr. <hi>Andrew Ker</hi> to be one of his Advocats.</p>
            <p>As to the Advocats Proteſtation, the Houſe reſolved, That they could not be allowed to ſpeak Treaſon either by word or Writ but upon their peril, only allowed them in the general, as much as in ſuch caſes was indulged to any. The Marquiſs and his Advocats being called in, my Lord Chancellor intimated the foreſaid Reſolutions of the Houſe, both in reference to my Lord Marquiſs, and to the Advocats Proteſtation.</p>
            <p>When my Lord Chancellor had done, the Marquiſs ſpoke as followeth;</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord Chancellor,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THere is one thing that had almoſt eſcaped me, anent that oppoſition at <hi>Stirling,</hi> 1948. That my Lord Advocate was ſpeaking of, That it may not ſtick with any of this honourable meeting, I ſhall ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly declare, that after the Defeat at <hi>Preſtoun,</hi> I was deſired to come and meet with the Committee of Eſtates (meaning thoſe who were in the then Engagement) And being come with ſome of my Friends to <hi>Stirling,</hi> fearing no harm, and ſuſpecting nothing, I was Invaded by Sir <hi>George Moure,</hi> where ſeveral of my Friends were killed, and my ſelf hardly eſcaped, which is all that can be ſaid I acted in Arms as many here knows.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, Not that I am any ways diffident; but I ſhall in due time clear every particular of that Libel; Yet I am not a little troubled that ſome who have heard the Calumnies therein; may let them have ſuch an impreſſion (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſerted with ſuch confidence) as to conceal a poſſibility, if not a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of their being true; I ſhall therefore deſire ſo much Charity from this honourable Meeting, that there be no hard thoughts entertained till I be fully heard.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:179730:5"/>
The Marquiſs therefore with the joynt concurrence of his Advocates, humbly deſired, that the Bill (containing many pungent Reaſons) for a precognition of his Proceſs, given to the Honourable Lords of Articles might be read and conſidered, in plene Parliament.</p>
            <p>To which my Lord Chancellor replyed, that it had been formerly refuſed at the Articles, and that it would not be granted.</p>
            <p>So his Lordſhip was carried back to the Caſtle.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proceedings">
            <head>
               <hi>Edinburh,</hi> March <hi>5. 1661.</hi> At the parliament Houſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Marquiſs <hi>of</hi> Argyle <hi>being called in, gave in a Bill containing ſeveral weighty Reaſons, deſiring a continuation till the Meeting of Parliament to Morrow. His Lordſhip being removed, after a long Debate, it was carried againſt him by two or three Votes; and his Lordſhip being called in, my Lord Chancellor told him it was refuſed, and ordered his Lordſhip to</hi> produce his Defences, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſpoke as followeth;</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY Lord Chancellor, This Buſineſs is of very great concernment to me, and not ſmall in the preparative of it to the whole Nation; Yea, it may concern many of your Lordſhips (who are ſitting here) and (your Poſterity;) And therefore I deſire to have your Grace (my Lord Commiſſioner) and the remanent Members of this honourable Meeting, your patience to hear me a ſew words without-prejudice or miſconſtruction, which any thing I can ſay is often obnoxious to.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall my Lord begin with the Words of that Godly King, <hi>Jehoſaphat that good</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> (after he was come back in peace to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) <hi>in his Inſtructions to his Judges, he deſires them to take heed what they do, for they judge not for Men, but for the</hi> LORD, <hi>who is with them in the Judgement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Lord, I ſhall ſpeak another Word to many young Men, who were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not Born, or ſo Young that it is impoſſible they could know the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe Buſineſſes, which are contained in the Libel againſt me (being all that hath been done ſince the Year. 1638,) ſo <hi>that</hi> they <hi>might have heard by report,</hi> what was <hi>done,</hi> but not why, or upon what Grounds, <hi>and what ſome</hi> have Suffered but not what they have deſerved.—Therefore I deſire your Lordſhips Charity, until all the particulars and ſeveral <hi>Circumſtances of every Particular be heard,</hi> without which no Man can Judge rightly of <hi>any</hi> Action. <hi>For as it is well obſerved by that incomparable</hi> Grotius, <hi>that</hi> Ariſtotle <hi>aſſerts, that there is more certainty in the Mathematicks than Morals, for as</hi> Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius <hi>has it, the Mathematicks ſeparates Forms from Matters, as betwixt Straight and Crooked there is no midſt, but in Morals, even the least Circumſtances vary the Matter, ſo that they are wont to have ſomething betwixt them, with ſuch Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, that the Acceſs is near ſometime to this, ſometime to that Extream; So that betwixt that which ought to be done, and that which ought not to be done, is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that which may be done,</hi> but is nearer now to this, than to the other
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179730:5"/>Extremity, or part, whence ambiguity often ariſeth? The particular Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances are ſo obvious to every underſtanding Man, that I need <hi>only to mention them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maxim</hi> 1. <hi>Polybius</hi> my Lord makes much of his Hiſtory depend upon theſe three, <hi>Concilia, Cauſa, et eventus;</hi> and there are likewiſe other three, <hi>Tempus, Locus, et Perſonae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Counſels, Cauſes, Events, Time, Place, Perſons.</note> 
                     <hi>The change whereof makes</hi> that which is lawful duty, unlawful, and on the contrary, ſo likewiſe in ſpeaking or repeating words, the adding or paring from them, will quite alter the ſence and meaning; as alſo in writing, the placing of the Comma's or Points, will change the ſentence to a quite other purpoſe than it was intended.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maxim</hi> 2. There is my Lord, another <hi>Maxim,</hi> which I do not mention as always undeniable; but when there is no lawful Magiſtrat exerciſing power and authority in a Nation, but an invading Uſurper in poſſeſſion, <hi>eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing former Laws, Crimes;</hi> In ſuch a caſe I ſay the ſafety of the people is the Supream Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maxim</hi> 3. There is another <hi>Maxim,</hi> which is not queſtioned by any, and it is, <hi>Neceſſity has no Law;</hi> for even the Moral Law of God yields to it, and Chriſt's Diſciples in <hi>Davids</hi> example: For this <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayes, <hi>Neceſſity</hi> (the defence of humane imbecility) <hi>breaks every Law; Nam neceſſitas legum irridet vincula,</hi> Neceſſity ſcorns the ſetters of Laws: So he that anſwers that Libel, The long Parliament revived, ſpeaking of this laſt Parliament (which his Majeſty calls, a bleſſed healing Parliament,) he ſays, the neceſſity to have it, may diſpenſe with ſome formalities: ſo <hi>Ravenella</hi> (ſo much eſteemed in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Scripture) after he has divided neceſſity in <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>hypothetick,</hi> makes that of ſubmitting to Powers of abſolute neceſſity: <hi>Joſephus</hi> alſo, my Lord, that famous Hiſtorian, when he mentioned <hi>Davids</hi> ſpeech to his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, after he had made <hi>Solomon</hi> (being but younger brother) King, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts them <q>to unity among themſelves, and ſubmiſſion to him and his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; for if it ſhould pleaſe God to bring a forraign ſword amongſt you you muſt ſubmit to them, much more then to him who is your brother, and one of your own Nation.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maxim</hi> 4. There is another <hi>Maxim,</hi> (my Lord) <hi>Inter arma ſilent leges;</hi> and it is well known, that divers retours and other things in <hi>Scotland,</hi> were done in conſideration of times of Peace, and times of War.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maxim</hi> 5. Another <hi>Maxim, Ex duobus malis minimum eligendum est cum unum eorum nequeunt evitari,</hi> ſays <hi>Aristotle, Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Quintilian, cum diverſa mala inter ſe comparantur minimum eorum locum boni occupat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maxim</hi> 6. There is another <hi>Maxim,</hi> 
                     <q>No mans intention muſt be judged by the event of any Action, there being oftentimes ſo wide a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the condition of a Work, and the intention of the Worker.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maxim</hi> 7. I ſhall only add another <hi>Maxim,</hi> 
                     <q>It cannot be eſteemed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, to abſtain from Vice; but where it is in our power to commit the Vice, and we meet with a Temptation.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>As I have named ſhortly ſome few <hi>Maxims,</hi> my Lord, I ſhall humbly ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome weighty Conſiderations to your Lordſhips thoughts:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſider.</hi> 1. The firſt Conſideration is, That there is different Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be had of Subjects actions when their lawful Magiſtrat is in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his Authority by himſelf, or others lawfully conſtituted by him, and when there is no King in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſider.</hi> 2. The ſecond is, That there is a different Conſideration betwixt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179730:6"/>the ſubjects actions, when the lawful Magiſtrat is in the Nation, and when he is put from it, and ſo forced to leave the people to the prevalent power of a Forraign Sword, and the Invader in poſſeſſion of Authority.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſider.</hi> 3. Thirdly, That there is a difference betwixt Subjects actions, even with the Invading Uſurper, after the Repreſentatives of a Nation have ſubmitted to, and accepted of their Authority and Government, and they in poſſeſſion ſeveral Years, the Nation acknowledging their Conſtitutions, and all the Lawyers preſſing and pleading them as Laws.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſider.</hi> 4. Fourthly, The actions of Subjects are to be conſidered, when aſſiſting the lawful Magiſtrat to their power, and never ſubmitting to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading Uſurper until they were priſoners; and could do no better.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſider.</hi> 5. Fifthly That there is likewiſe conſideration to be had of the actions of ſuch Subjects, being ſtill priſoners upon demand under Articles to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſider.</hi> 6. Sixtly, It is to be conſidered likewiſe of the actions of ſuch a Subject, who was particularly noticed and perſecuted by the Invader, for his affection to the lawful Magiſtrat and his Government.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſider.</hi> 7. Seventhly, It is to be conſidered, that there is a great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt Actions done <hi>ad lucrum captandum,</hi> and thoſe done <hi>ad damnum evitandum;</hi> that is to ſay, Actions to procure Benefit, and Actions to ſhun de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſider.</hi> 8. Eightly, It is to be conſidered, that there hath ever been a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable conſideration had, by any Prince, of any perſon coming voluntar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and caſting himſelf upon a Princes Clemency.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſider.</hi> 9. Ninthly, It is to be conſidered, that his Majeſty himſelf hath a gracious natural Inclination unto Clemency and Mercy, which hath been ſo abundantly manifeſted to his Subjects in <hi>England,</hi> even to all (except to ſome of the immediat Murtherers of his Royal Father) that it cannot be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the ſame will be wanting to his People in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who ſuffered by them (whom his Majeſty hath graciouſly pardoned) even for their dutiful Service, and affection to his Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>Therefore without thought of any prejudice to the Parliament, or this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Meeting, I muſt make uſe of my Lord Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> his words, though in another caſe, ſaying, <hi>There cannot too much evil befal thoſe who do the beſt they can to corrupt his Majesties good Nature, and to extinguiſh his Clemency:</hi> For his Majeſties ſelf declared his Natural Inclination to Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, in his Speech to both his Houſes of Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> whom he hath (with all his people) <hi>conjured, deſired, and commanded, to aboliſh all Notes of Diſcord, Separations, and difference of Parties, and to lay aſide all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Animoſities, and the memory of paſt Provocations, and to return to a perfect <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity amongſt themſelves under his Majesties Protections;</hi> which is hoped all your Lordſhips will concur in, having ſo worthy a Pattern to follow: And as theſe are his Majeſties Inclinations expreſt, ſo it is ſuitable to the <hi>Arms</hi> he bears as <hi>King of Scotland,</hi> which is the <hi>Lyon,</hi> whoſe Motto is known to all.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>— <hi>Nobilis est ira Leonis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Parcere ſubjectis, &amp; debellare ſuperbos.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Which is to ſay, To vanquiſh and ſubdue the Proud, and ſpare ſuch as are ſubmiſſive; of the which Number I am one: And for that effect, in all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, preſent this humble <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to his Majeſty, and your Grace, my <hi>Lord Commiſſioner</hi> in his Majeſties Name.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
